Finding Aid for Leslie Bassett Papers, 1946-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Sound Recordings
  - A Ring of Emeralds, Notes in the Silence, 1967 January 22, 1982 March 10, 1985 November 25, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-152-1-2]; mp3 file; (Premiere performance of Notes in the Silence by University of Michigan Chamber Choir, conducted by Thos. Hilbish. January 22, 1967; Notes in the Silence University of Michigan Choir conducted by Patrick Gardner, November 25, 1985.)
  - Duo Concert ante Premiere; Dialogues for Oboe and Piano Premiere, 1988 April 06, 1985 May 21, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-154-1]; mp3 file; (Duo Concert ante Premiere Stephen Jordheim, alto saxophone, Ted Rehl, piano, May 21, 1985; Dialogues for Oboe and Piano. Performers are Barry Kroeker, Steven Smith, at Penn State University; Premiere April 6, 1988 )
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-154-2]; mp3 file; (Duo Concert ante Premiere Stephen Jordheim, alto saxophone, Ted Rehl, piano, May 21, 1985; Dialogues for Oboe and Piano. Performers are Barry Kroeker, Steven Smith, at Penn State University; Premiere April 6, 1988 )
  - Concerto Grosso for Brass Quintet with Wind and Percussion Ensemble, 1983 February 04, 1983 February 20, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-155-1-1]; mp3 file; (February 20, 1983 performance of Concerto Grosso for Brass Quintet with Wind and Percussion Ensemble. University of Michigan Wind Ensemble, H. Robert Reynolds, conductor. Robert Sullivan and Patrick Reynolds, trumpets, Lisa Ormston, horn; Robert a Smit, trombone; Henry Charles Smith, bass trombone. At Alice Tully Hall, New York.)
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-155-1-2]; mp3 file; (February 4, 1983 performance of Concerto Grosso for Brass Quintet with Wind and Percussion Ensemble. University of Michigan Wind Ensemble, H. Robert Reynolds, conductor. Robert Sullivan and Patrick Reynolds, trumpets, Lisa Ormston, horn; Robert a Smit, trombone; Henry Charles Smith, bass trombone. At Hill Auditorium.)
  - Fantasy for Clarinet and Wind Ensemble Premiere, 1987 October 02, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-156-1]; mp3 file; (Fantasy for Clarinet and Wind Ensemble Premiere Hill Auditorium, Ann Arbor. Fred Ormand, Clarinet, University of Michigan Wind Ensemble, H. Robert Reynolds, conducting.)
  - Preludes; Duo Concert ante, 1985 May 21, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-158-1]; mp3 file; (Preludes premiere performance. Benning Dexter, piano. Rackham Auditorium February 16, 1985.)
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-158-2]; mp3 file; (Duo Concert ante copy of premiere at Carnegie Hall. Stephen Jordheim, Alto Saxophone, Ted Rehl, piano. May 21, 1985.)
  - Collect, electronic tape only, mono and stereo, [1968 and 1969], Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-159-1]; mp3 file; (Produced in the Electronic Music Studies of the University of Michigan. This music (with Soprano, Alto, Tenor, and Baritone) is published by World Library Publications. Box indicates that this recording contains both the stereo and mono versions of the tape, but complete recording is stereo.)
  - Of Wind and Earth; Collect, 1969 October 29, 1971 January 11, 1975 October 23, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-160-1]; mp3 file; (Multiple recordings spliced together on one segment of tape. Band 1: Of Wind and Earth UM Chamber Choir, Thos Hilbish conducting at Hill Auditorium October 23, 1975; Collect, University of Michigan Chamber Choir, Thos Hilbish, conducting. Contemporary Music Fest. October 29, 1969 and Collect performed by Eastern Michigan University Madrigal Singers, Emily Lowe conducting. January 11, 1971.)
  - Forces Premiere, 1973 May 01, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-161-1]; mp3 file; (Forces performed by Drake University Orchestra (rehearsal and premiere performance) May 1, 1973, Includes program in tape box. Performers are the Drake University Orchestra conducted by Thomas Griswold, with solos by Wilfred Biel, violin; John Ehrlich, cello; Kenneth Drake, piano.)
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-161-2]; mp3 file; (Forces performed by Drake University Orchestra (rehearsal and premiere performance) May 1, 1973, Includes program in tape box. Performers are the Drake University Orchestra conducted by Thomas Griswold, with solos by Wilfred Biel, violin; John Ehrlich, cello; Kenneth Drake, piano.)
  - Eclogue Encomium and Evocation 1962, [1962?], 1966 January 13, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 and 15 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-163-1-1]; mp3 file; (Eclogue Encomium and Evocation (first performance) 1962 Women's Choir of Eastern Michigan University conducted by Emily Lowe at Pease Auditorium performance.)
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-163-1-2]; mp3 file; (Eclogue Encomium and Evocation (first performance) 1962 Women's Choir of Eastern Michigan University conducted by Emily Lowe at Pease Auditorium performance.)
  - Sonata for Violin and Piano; Five Pieces for String Quartet, 1960, 1961 January 09, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-164-1]; mp3 file; (Sonata for Violin and Piano performed by Gustave Rosseels, violin and Wallace Berry, piano at Rackham Lecture Hall from broadcast January 9, 1961; Five Pieces for String Quartet Rackham Lecture Hall by the Stanley Quartet from broadcast in the Summer of 1960.)
  - Quintet for Piano and Strings, 1962 June 10, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-165-1]; mp3 file; (Quintet for Piano and Strings performed by the Societa Cameristica Italiana at the American Academy in Rome June 10, 1962. Performers are Aldo Redditi, Umberto Oliveti, violins; Emilio Poggioni, viola; Italo Gomex, cello; Guiliana Zaccagnini, piano.)
  - Music of Leslie Bassett performed on the 27th Annual Symposium of Contemporary Music, Texas Tech University, 1978 January 23-February 2, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-175-1]; mp3 file; (Four Statements; Toccata; Quartet for Trombones; Trio for Trumpet, Horn and Trombone; Wind Music, Five Movements for Wind Sextet; Nonet; Notes in the Silence; Designs, Images and Textures; Sonata for Trombone and Piano. Contains program inside tape box listing performers and other information about Bassett.)
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-175-2]; mp3 file; (Four Statements; Toccata; Quartet for Trombones; Trio for Trumpet, Horn and Trombone; Wind Music, Five Movements for Wind Sextet; Nonet; Notes in the Silence; Designs, Images and Textures; Sonata for Trombone and Piano. Contains program inside tape box.)
  - Music for film The Locks of Sault Ste. Marie; Cantata "For City, Nation, World", 1955, 1960 February 21, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-181-1]; mp3 file; (Music for film "The Locks of Sault Ste. Marie"; film made by the UM audiovisual Department 1955 Orchestra conducted by William Boyer.)
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-181-2]; mp3 file; (Cantata "For City, Nation, World" based on hymn in Lutheran Hymnal, Three Choir Festival, Holy Trinity Lutheran Church, Buffalo, New York. Conducted by Hans Vigeland, John Hoffman, organist. Dated: February 21, 1960.)
  - Five Love Songs, 1983 February 25, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-182-1]; mp3 file; (Five Love Songs, Janice Horsanyi, soprano and Nancy Revzen, piano. February 25, 1983 Florida State University in Tallahassee, Florida.)
  - Temperaments; Salute, 1989 February, 1983, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-184-1]; mp3 file; (Temperaments performed by Michael Lorimer on guitar as a trial run performance from a 1983 cassette recording.)
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-184-2]; mp3 file; (Salute for Five Trumpets recorded in Eau Claire, Wisconsin in late February 1989.)
  - Concerto for Two Pianos and Orchestra premiere; Sounds, Shapes and Symbols premiere, 1977 April 30, 1978 March 17, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-188-1]; mp3 file; (Concerto for Two Pianos and Orchestra premiere April 30, 1977. Performers are Nelita True and Fernando Laires, piano; Midland Symphony Orchestra conducted by Don. Tho. Jaeger.)
    - [Part 2], [0601-SR-188-2]; mp3 file; (University of Michigan Symphony Band conducted by H. Robert Reynolds performing "Sounds, Shapes and Symbols" at Hill Auditorium premiere March 17,1978)
  - WUOM Studio Showcase, compositions of Leslie Bassett, 1952 August 12, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 15 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-189-1]; mp3 file; (Leslie Bassetts compositions showcased on WUOM. Compositions performed are: "Three Madrigal Songs" and "Sonata for Cello and Piano." )
  - School of Music Program, Leslie Bassett and Anita Bassett performers, includes Sonata for Trombone and Piano, 1955 July 17, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 10.5 inch, 7 1/2 ips
    - [Part 1], [0601-SR-190-1]; mp3 file; (Bassett Sonata for Trombone and Piano; Finney Elegy and March; Hindemith Sonata for Trombone and Piano; Marini Sinfonia, La Giustiniana; canzona, La Marina; Sonata No. 9; Sinfonia No. 3; Sonata, La Foscarina. Includes program in tape box.)
  - Cassette tapes (Box 11)
  - Phonograph discs (Box 46)
  - Phonograph discs (Box 47)
    continued
- Musical Compositions by Leslie Bassett
  Bassett's Musical Compositions are arranged into broad classifications: Orchestra Music; Music for Wind Ensemble or Band; Chamber Music; Choral Music; Music for Brass; Music for Solo Voice; Unaccompanied Instrumental Solos; Organ Music; and Piano Music. These categories include only compositions which have been published. These are arranged chronologically by date of composition; copyright date, when known, is included. The kinds of material found within the individual file varies, but can include original manuscripts, publisher's galley proofs, and published score. In addition, this series includes those compositions written for his master of music and doctorate degrees as well as miscellaneous and unpublished musical compositions.
  - Orchestra Music
    - Five Movements for Orchestra 1961 (Box 12)
    - Variations for Orchestra 1963 (©1966) (Box 12)
      (LB won the Pulitzer Prize in 1966)
    - Variations for Orchestra 1963 (©1966) (Volume 1)
    - Colloquy 1968 (©1969) (Box 12)
    - Colloquy 1968 (©1969) (Box 42)
    - Celebration in Praise of Earth 1970 (©1971) (Box 13)
    - Celebration in Praise of Earth 1970 (©1971) (Volume 2)
    - Forces 1972 (©1973) (Box 13)
    - Echoes from an Invisible World 1974-1975 (©1976) (Box 14)
    - Echoes from an Invisible World 1974-1975 (©1976) (Volume 3)
    - Echoes from an Invisible World 1974-1975 (©1976) (Box 42)
    - Concerto for Two Pianos and Orchestra 1976 (©1977) (Box 15)
    - Concerto for Two Pianos and Orchestra 1976 (©1977) (Volume 4)
    - Concerto for Two Pianos and Orchestra 1976 (©1977) (Box 42)
    - Concerto Lirico for Trombone and Orchestra 1983 (©1984) (Box 15)
    - Concerto Lirico for Trombone and Orchestra 1983 (©1984) (Box 42)
    - From a Source Evolving 1985 (©1986) (Box 15)
    - From a Source Evolving 1985 (©1986) (Box 42)
    - Concerto for Orchestra 1991 (©1991) (Concerto for Brass and Orchestra) (Box 42)
    - Thoughts that Sing, Breathe and Burn 1995 (©1996) (Box 43)
    - Concerto for Alto Saxophone and Orchestra 1999 ©2000 (Box 43)
  - Music for Wind Ensemble or Band
    - Designs, Images and Textures 1964 (©1966) (Box 16)
    - Designs, Images and Textures 1964 (©1966) (Box 44)
    - Sounds, Shapes and Symbols 1977 (©1978) (Box 16)
    - Sounds, Shapes and Symbols 1977 (©1978) (Box 44)
    - Concerto Grosso 1982 (©1983) (Box 16)
    - Concerto Grosso 1982 (©1983) (Box 44)
    - Colors and Contours 1984 (©1985) (Box 16)
    - Lullaby (for Kirsten) 1985 (©1990) (Box 44)
    - Fantasy for Clarinet and Wind Ensemble 1986 (©1987) (Box 17)
    - Fantasy for Clarinet and Wind Ensemble 1986 (©1987) (Box 44)
    - Wood and Reed Transformed 1998 (©1999) (Box 17)
    - Wood and Reed Transformed 1998 (©1999) (Box 44)
  - Chamber Music
    - Trio for Viola, Clarinet and Piano 1953 (Box 18)
    - Quintet for Strings 1954 (Box 18)
    - Clarinet Duets 1955 (©1956, 1977) (Box 18)
    - Sonata for Viola and Piano 1956 (Box 18)
    - Sonata for Violoncello and Piano 1950 (Box 18)
    - Five Pieces for String Quartet 1957 (©1960) (Box 18)
    - Woodwind Quintet 1958 (Box 18)
    - Cello Duets 1959 (Box 18)
    - Sonata for Violin and Piano 1959 (Box 18)
    - Quintet for Piano and Strings 1962 (Box 18)
    - Third String Quartet, 1962. (Box 19)
    - Music for Cello and Piano 1966 (©1971) (Box 19)
    - Nonet 1967 (©1969) (Box 19)
    - Nonet 1967 (©1969) (Volume 5)
    - Music for Saxophone and Piano 1968 (©1969) (Box 19)
    - Sextet for Piano and Strings 1971 (©1975) (Box 20)
    - Sextet for Piano and Strings 1971 (©1975) (Box 44)
    - Sounds Remembered 1972 (©1975) (Box 21)
    - Wind Music 1975 (©1977) (Box 21)
    - Sextet for flutes, clarinets, and strings 1979 (©1982) (Box 21)
    - Fourth String Quartet 1978 (©1980) (Box 21)
    - Trio for Violin, Clarinet and Piano 1980 (©1982) (Box 21)
    - Concerto da Camera 1981 (©1982) (Box 22)
    - Duo Concertante 1984 (©1988) (Box 22)
    - Dialogues 1987 (©1990) (Box 22)
    - Pierrot Songs 1988 (©1990) (Box 22)
    - Duo-Inventions, (two cellos) 1988 (©1990) (Box 23)
    - Illuminations 1989 (©1990) (Box 23)
    - Arias for Clarinet and Piano 1992 (©1993) (Box 23)
    - Narratives, (guitar quartet) 1993 (©1995) (Box 23)
    - Trio-Inventions 1996 (Box 23)
    - Three Graces 2000 (Box 23)
  - Choral Music
    - The Lamb, text by William Blake 1952 (Box 24)
    - Out of the Depths, Ps. 130 1957 (Box 24)
    - Cantata, For City, Nation, World, Lutheran hymns and other texts 1959 (Box 24)
    - Moonrise, text by D H Lawrence 1960 (Box 24)
    - Remembrance, text by Hoover Rupert 1960 (©1968) (Box 24)
    - Eclogue, Encomium and Evocation, text from Song of Songs 1962 (Box 24)
    - Follow Now that Bright Star (Christmas carol) 1962 (©1977) (Box 24)
    - Hear My Prayer, O Lord, text from Psalm 64 1965 (©1967) (Box 24)
    - Prayers for Divine Service, Latin texts 1965 (Box 24)
    - Notes in the Silence, texts from Dag Hammarskjold's Markings, 1966 (©1973) (Box 24)
    - Collect, text a prayer for peace 1969 (©1970) (Box 25)
    - Moon Canticle, texts from numerous sources concerning the moon 1969 (©1971) (Box 25)
    - Of Wind and Earth, texts by Shelley, William Conan Bryant, St. Francis 1973 (©1978) (Box 25)
    - A Ring of Emeralds, 5 movements with assorted Irish texts 1979 (©1981) (Box 25)
    - Sing to the Lord, text from Psalm 95 1981 (©1987) (Box 25)
    - Lord, Who Hast Formed Me, text by George Herbert 1981 (©1987) (Box 25)
    - Whoe'er She Be, text by Robert Crashaw 1986 (©1989) (Box 25)
    - Whoe'er She Be, text by Robert Crashaw 1986 (©1989) (Box 44)
    - Almighty, Eternal, text by L. Bassett 1990 (©1994) (Box 25)
    - Almighty, Eternal, text by L. Bassett 1990 (©1994) (Box 44)
    - Maker of our Being, text by L. Bassett 1993 (©1995) (Box 25)
  - Music for Brass
    - Quartet for Trombones 1949 (©1954) (Box 26)
    - Sonata for Horn and Piano 1952 (©1954) (Box 26)
    - Brass Trio 1953 (©1968) (Box 26)
    - Sonata for Trombone and Piano 1954 (©1954) (Box 26)
    - Suite for Unaccompanied Trombone 1957 (Box 26)
    - 12 Duos for Two or Four Trombones 1974 (©1978) (Box 26)
    - Salute 1985 (©1985) (Box 26)
    - Brass Quintet 1988 (©1991) (Box 26)
    - Song and Dance 1993 (©1998) (Box 26)
  - Music for Solo Voice
    - Four Songs, texts Wm. Blake, Geo. Herbert, Edwin A. Robinson 1953 (Box 27)
    - To Music, texts by Ben Jonson, Robert Herrick, Wm. Billings 1962 (©1966) (Box 27)
    - The Jade Garden, four oriental poems in English 1973 (©1977) (Box 27)
    - Time and Beyond, texts by Emerson, Tagore, Mark Van Doren 1973 (©1980) (Box 27)
    - Love Songs (Five Love Songs for Soprano and Piano), texts from anon. Greek, W S Landor, Anne Bradstreet, Emerson, Henry Harrington 1975 (©1977) (Box 27)
    - Two Stephens Songs The Shell and The Lion (In Waste Places), poems by James Stephens, 1996-1998 (Box 27)
  - Unaccompanied Instrumental Solos
    - Soliloquies 1976 (©1978) (Box 28)
    - Temperaments (five) 1979-1983 (©1984) (Box 28)
    - Metamorphoses, 8 pieces for solo bassoon 1990 (©1992) (Box 28)
    - Song of the Aulos (Box 28)
  - Organ Music
    - Voluntaries 1958 (Box 28)
    - Four Statements 1964 (Box 28)
    - Liturgies (6 movements) 1980 (©1984) (Box 28)
  - Piano Music
    - Six Piano Pieces 1951 (Box 29)
    - Mobile 1961 (©1979) (Box 29)
    - Elaborations 1966 (©1983) (Box 29)
    - Preludes (seven) 1984 (©1988) (Box 29)
    - Configurations 1987 (©1988) (Box 29)
  - Compositions for Degrees
    - Second Symphony 1956 (Box 30)
      (composition for doctorate)
    - Second Symphony 1956 (Box 31)
      (composition for doctorate) continued
    - Symphony in B 1949, 2 volumes; 153 pages (Box 32)
      (one of two compositions written for M.M. degree)
    - Designs in Brass: Two Movements for Brass Choir 1949 (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous and unpublished
    - Easter Triptych (Box 33)
      (published 1962)
    - Kindergarten Songs (Box 33)
    - Four Metrical Psalms (Box 33)
    - Toccata for Organ (Box 33)
      (published 1957)
    - Ballad of Lee B.B. (Box 33)
    - Short Response for After Prayer 1973 (Box 33)
    - Introit: Sing Praise to the Lord (First United Methodist Church) 1992 (Box 33)
    - Masque of Bells (Box 33)
    - Movement for Violin, Cello and Piano Trio (unpublished) (Box 34)
    - Music for film "The Locks of Sault Ste. Marie" (Box 34)
    - Fanfare (Box 34)
    - String Quartet #1 (Box 34)
    - String Quarter #2 (Box 34)
    - Trombones in the Instrumental Ensembles of Biagio Marini 1955 (Box 34)
    - Chorale and Invocation (Box 35)
    - Two miniatures for Band (Box 35)
    - Sound, Drums and Trumpets (Box 35)
    - Sonorities and Lines (Box 35)
    - Hammered Strings and Whistling Pipes (Box 36)
    - Chamber Music for 4 horns (Box 36)
    - Organ Music (Box 36)
    - Family History (Box 36)
    - Incidental Music for the Tempest 1950 (Box 36)
    - Overture (Box 36)
    - Short Overture (Box 36)
    - Sketch and manuscript for "A Slow Movement for Orchestra" (Box 45)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 45)
    - Symphonic Sketch (Box 37)
- Compositions of others
  The Compositions of others series consists of musical compositions either autographed and inscribed to Leslie Bassett by friends, colleagues, and students or which contain marginal or other notations by Bassett, and which, therefore, might give indication of his method of teaching and/or composition.
  - Compositions of works inscribed to Leslie Bassett by colleagues, students, and others (Box 38)
  - Compositions used in his teaching and study and containing some notations by Leslie Bassett (Box 38)
  - Compositions of works inscribed to Leslie Bassett by colleagues, students, and others (Box 39)
  - Compositions used in his teaching and study and containing some notations by Leslie Bassett (Box 39)
  - Compositions of works inscribed to Leslie Bassett by colleagues, students, and others (Box 40)
  - Compositions used in his teaching and study and containing some notations by Leslie Bassett (Box 40)
  - Compositions of works inscribed to Leslie Bassett by colleagues, students, and others (Box 41)
  - Compositions used in his teaching and study and containing some notations by Leslie Bassett (Box 41)
Related resources
Additional biographical information as well as comprehensive lists of his major works can be found on his personal website at http://www.lesliebassett.com/ and in Ellen Johnson's book Leslie Bassett: a bio-bibliography (1994).